原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
翻译     青椒 鱼小渊 莫达 阿蘇駅 x6324
校对     木浅
后期     吉吉
总监     somehacker
有了吗
Has it come on?
没有
No.
现在呢
Now?
没有
No.
现在呢
Now?
没有
No.
现在呢
Now?
你快点转个方向
Turn the damn thing properly!
欢迎收看首尔奥林匹克运动会摔跤比赛
Welcome to the wrestling area at the Seoul Olympics.
非常期待看到今天的对决
Looking forward to an exciting match today.
有了
It's come on.
那我下去了
Shall I come down?
别
No.
你就在上面扶着
Stand there holding it.
本次奥运会的最后一场  72公斤级别
The final match this Olympics... in the 72-kilo category,
俄罗斯对美国
between wrestlers from Russia and America.
真的很可惜
It's really sad that,
摔跤在印度人气如此之高
despite wrestling being such a popular sport in India
印度摔跤手却至今未在奥运会拿过金牌
Indian wrestlers have disappointed in the Olympics.
我们的孩子都能拿金牌回来
Even our boys can bring home medals.
可是哪有人支持
But where is the support?
没资金  没设施
Neither money, nor facilities.
我们的孩子怎么拿金牌
How will our boys win a medal?
要是拿金牌靠嘴说
If a medal could be won with words,
你大概很早就拿到了
you would have won it a long time ago.
你是新来的吗
Are you new here?
我想也是
That's what I thought.
有空踏进摔跤场试试吧
Try stepping into a wrestling arena someday,
比赛还没开始你就要逃命了
you'll run for your life before the match begins.
看来你经验丰富
Looks like you have done it many times.
还没比赛就逃跑
Run for your life.
这里要是摔跤场  就知道谁会逃跑了
If this were an arena, then we'd see who would run.
何必非要摔跤场
Why do we need an arena?
大家翘首以盼的时刻终于来了
Now, the moment we were all waiting for.
角逐场已经准备好
The stage is all set for a big fight.
场上气氛急剧升温
There's palpable excitement in the air.
摔跤手都在走动
Both the wrestlers are walking,
准备开战
for the fight.
你说得没错  汤姆
You are absolutely right, Tom.
看来这次比赛会十分精彩
Looks like it's going to be an interesting bout.
观众也非常兴奋
The crowd seems excited.
摔跤手已经针锋相对
The wrestlers come face to face.
我们拭目以待
Let's see how it plays out.
礼节性握手
The customary handshake.
裁判吹哨  比赛开始
The referee's whistle... and the match begins!
胜负已分
He's down!
看来俄罗斯选手出师不利
An early thrashing for the Russian wrestler.
过度自信往往会带来灾难
Overconfidence can often prove fatal.
兄弟  要再试一次吗
Bro, you want to try once more?
两位摔跤手开始准备下一轮对决
Now, the wrestlers are gearing up for the next round.
没错汤姆  这场比赛并没有预料中轻松
Yes, Tom, this match doesn't look as easy as it had seemed.
来看看接下来会如何吧
Let's see what happens now.
两位摔跤手开始互相试探
Both wrestlers testing each other.
来势汹汹的攻击  同样精彩的防守
A great attack! An equally superb defense.
这一招非常漂亮
And that was a magnificent move!
这动作太完美
What an amazing move!
他根本没反应过来
He didn't know what hit him.
一方出击
Here's an attack.
对方迅速反击
And that's a counter-attack!
比赛结束
And it's over!
非常明显
It's all over.
结局类似大卫与巨人歌利亚
David has become Goliath,
但大卫仿佛拥有了巨人的力量
and Goliath has become David here.
说得好  汤姆
Well said, Tom.
谁都没想到俄罗斯选手会这么快被淘汰
No one expected such a quick defeat for the Russian wrestler.
真精彩
What a match!
不愧是顶级摔跤比赛
This is top class wrestling.
身手不错
You are good.
你打败了邦冠军
You've just defeated a state level champion.
不必难过
Don't be disheartened buddy,
打败你的是全国冠军
you've just lost to a national level champion.
这是我叔叔
Meet my uncle.
马哈维亚·辛格·珀尕
Mahavir Singh Phogat.
多年前他离开了摔跤
He quit wrestling many years ago,
但摔跤却没有离开他
but wrestling hasn't quit on him.
小个子快赢了
The smaller kid will win.
干得漂亮
There you go!
摔跤光靠身材高大是不管用的
Merely building a good body does not make a wrestler.
过来  孩子
Come here, kid.
摔跤手是天生的  必须有天赋
Wrestling runs in the blood, you have to be born with it.
给  买点牛奶喝吧
Here. Buy yourself some milk.
祝你好运
Bless you.
等盘子里没饭了你吃什么  吃金牌吗
When there's no food on your plate what will you eat? Medals?
没人在乎摔跤
No one gives a damn about wrestling.
接受你面前的工作机会吧
Just take up the job you are being offered.
你为什么放弃摔跤
Why did you quit wrestling?
我别无选择
I had no choice.
摔跤带给了我尊重  名誉
Wrestling gave me respect, fame,
却带不来钱
but it couldn't give me money.
所以我就接受了这份工作
So, I took up this job.
每位摔跤手
Every wrestler dreams,
都希望能够为国家赢得荣誉
of bringing honor and glory to the country.
可如果国家不提供任何帮助
But if the country offers no support,
一名摔跤手能走多远
how far can a wrestler go?
没能为国家
It's not your fault that
拿到金牌不是你的错
you couldn't win a medal for your country.
你要让这些回忆折磨你多久
How long will you let these memories depress you?
我做不到的  我们的儿子会做到
What I couldn't do, our son will.
他会为国家捧金而归
He will win gold for our country.
我们的国旗会高高飘扬
Our flag will fly the highest.
你记住我的话
Mark my words.
那天叔叔紧张得像个孩子
That day uncle was as anxious as a student,
在焦急等待高考成绩
whose high school results were due.
别担心  弟弟
Don't worry, brother.
不会有事的
It's going to be alright.
是女孩
It's a girl.
叔叔想要个男孩
Uncle was hoping for a boy.
却生了个女孩
But a girl was born.
没关系
It's okay.
你有妹妹啦  奥姆卡尔
You have a sister now, Omkar.
我是打心眼里高兴
I was genuinely happy.
可叔叔却在强颜欢笑
But uncle was faking it.
后来一发不可收拾
And then it all started.
忽然村里所有人都成了专家
Suddenly everyone in the village was an expert,
都知道怎样能生儿子了
in the art of conceiving a boy.
用白芝麻籽做甜品  喂给一头黑奶牛
Feed a black cow sweets made with white sesame seeds,
要用玉米煎饼包好  在日出前用左手喂
wrapped in maize flatbreads, with your left hand, before sunrise.
绝对能生儿子
A son, for sure!
马哈维亚  这是份祷词  求儿子的
Mahavir, here's a special prayer... for a son.
你要每天吟诵
Recite it daily.
来  吃了这个
Here... eat this.
快吃
Eat this!
别走呀
Stop, will you.
马哈维亚
Mahavir,
你一定要在周日行房
make sure you try only on a Sunday.
其他日子  都要忍住
On all other days, reign in your urges.
明白吗
Got it?
人们的建议层出不穷
Neither did people stop giving their advice,
孩子  给你
Here you go, son.
叔叔婶婶也在不停尝试
Nor did uncle and aunt stop acting on them.
婶婶生孩子那天  大半个村的人都来了
The day of the delivery arrived and so did half the village.
等着证明自己的方法管用
To take credit for a son.
吉塔  你要有弟弟啦
Geeta, you are going to have a brother.
可以跟他一起玩
You can play with him.
是女孩
It's a girl.
但叔叔没等来儿子
But neither did uncle get a son,
村民们也没等到赞赏
nor the villagers, credit.
但这些"屡试不爽的妙招"里
But, in all these "Unfailing techniques",
出了什么错呢
where did the fault lie?
她肯定喂了头黑水牛  必须喂黑奶牛
She must have fed a black buffalo instead of a black cow.
不信看我家住在罗塔克的表亲
Else, look at my cousin from Rohtak.
三年连续生了三个大胖小子
She had three healthy boys in three years.
要是祷词念反了
If you say the prayer in reverse,
结果肯定也是反的呀
the results will also be reversed.
自制力是美德
Self control is a virtue.
我让他只在周日行房
I told him to try only on Sundays.
他肯定是没控制住
He must have let the reins free every day.
我没能给你生个儿子
I couldn't give you a son...
不怪你
It's not your fault.
你别误会
And don't get me wrong.
我很爱吉塔和芭比塔
Both, Geeta and Babita are very dear to me.
但只有儿子能完成我的梦想
But only a boy can fulfill my dream.
许多年过去了
Years went by.
叔叔坚持不懈
Uncle remained adamant,
他想要儿子
he wanted a boy.
可也许上帝也很执着
But maybe God was adamant too.
第三胎是女孩
The third child was a girl,
第四胎也是
and so was the fourth.
这次连我也很沮丧
This time I too was dejected.
饭好了  爸爸
Food is ready, papa.
翻个面  不然要烧焦了
Turn it over or it'll burn.
在那之后  叔叔就放弃了
After that uncle gave up
对儿子的渴望  也放弃了梦想
on his desire for a son, and on his dream too.
马哈维亚·辛格先生好
Hey, Mahavir Singh-ji!
他这是怎么了
What's wrong with him?
今晚的摔跤比赛你要去看吗
Are you coming to watch the wrestling match this evening?
不了  你去吧
No. You carry on.
马哈维亚
Hey, Mahavir!
我刚生了个儿子
I've been blessed with a boy.
来  吃些糕点吧
Here... have some sweets.
怎么回事
What happened?
你看他们被打成什么样了
Look how badly they've been thrashed.
你说话啊
Say something!
是啊  你看他们被打成什么样了
Yes, look how badly they've been thrashed.
鼻青脸肿的
They're all swollen and bruised.
是啊  鼻青脸肿的
Yes, they're all swollen and bruised.
你为什么打人家
Why did you beat them?
我没打  叔叔
I didn't, uncle.
是吉塔和芭比塔打的
Geeta and Babita beat them up.
是他们先挑衅的
They started it.
他说我是蠢货  还说芭比塔是巫婆
He called me a loser and Babita a witch.
于是我们就教训了他们一下
So, we gave it to them.
至于打这么狠吗  就这么小的事
They beat them so badly? For such a trivial reason?
对  不该打这么狠
Yes, shouldn't have beaten them so badly.
请原谅她们  她们还是孩子
Please forgive them... they're kids.
我们不追究  是因为那是你家孩子
We are letting go because they are your girls.
快走
Move!
被俩女孩打成这样
Got thrashed by girls!
过来
Come here.
Come here!
我们不会再打架了  爸爸
We won't fight again, papa.
先告诉我  你们是怎么打的
First tell me, how did you manage to do it?
一开始他骂我是蠢货  我没理他
First, he called me a loser but I remained quiet.
可后来他说芭比塔是巫婆
But then he called Babita a witch.
我就怒了
That was it.
我抓住他  直接给了一拳
I grabbed him and punched him like this.
后来另一个人过来了
Then the other guy attacked.
我抓着他头发  直接把他拽倒
I caught his hair and shoved him down,
一肘敲在他背上
and dug my elbow in his back.
人们说溺水的人见到稻草都会看到希望
They say that a twig is enough to give hope to a drowning man.
这下叔叔找到了两根稻草
Here, uncle had found not one, but two lifeguards!
一直以来  我想要个儿子
All along, I was desperate for a son,
让儿子为国家赢得金牌
so he could win a gold for the country.
但我从没想过  金牌就是金牌
But what didn't occur to me is that gold is gold.
不管是男孩赢的  还是女孩
Whether a boy wins it, or a girl.
今后不要让吉塔和芭比塔做家务了
From now on, Geeta and Babita will do no household chores.
她们是天生的摔跤手
Wrestling is in their blood.
从今往后只专注于摔跤
From now on they will only wrestle.
摔跤是男孩干的
Wrestling is for boys.
你觉得咱家闺女们不如男孩吗
You think our girls are any lesser than boys?
我从来没见过女孩摔跤
I've never ever seen girls wrestle.
村里人会怎么说
What will the villagers say?
村里人能说多久
For how long will they talk?
要是孩子们断了手和腿怎么办
What if the girls break their hands and legs?
那就治
We'll fix them.
我们上哪儿去找资金
Where will the money come from?
不知道
I don't know.
别为了你的热情毁掉她们的人生
Don't ruin the girls' lives for your passion.
给我一年时间
Let me try for a year.
这一年  你忍住自己的感情
For this one year, you bury your feelings.
如果我错了
If I'm proven wrong,
我就永远放弃我的梦想
I'll bury my dream forever.
明天五点来见我
Be ready at 5am tomorrow.
为什么  爸爸
Why, papa?
带你们去吃最爱的零食  油炸面团
I want to feed you your favourite snack, 'gol gappas'.
五点  记住了
5am. Okay?
你又闯了什么祸
What did you do now?
我以为是你呢
I thought you did something.
吃吧
Eat.
好吃吗
How is it?
不够辣  爸爸
It's a little less spicy, papa.
行  多放辣
Alright, make it spicier.
想吃多少吃多少
Eat as much as you want right now.
从今往后  你们都要练习摔跤
Because from today, you will both lead the life of a wrestler.
摔跤手不允许
And wrestlers are not allowed,
吃腌制和油腻辛辣的食物
pickled, oily and spicy food,
你们喜欢的基本都不能吃
in fact, all the food that you most love.
这是最后的盛宴了
Consider this your last treat.
加快速度  芭比塔
Come on, faster Babita!
爸爸  穿这样的衣服太难跑了
Papa, it's difficult to run in these clothes.
不许停
Don't you dare stop!
不过就是打了几个男孩
Nobody would've ever been punished so severely,
为什么要惩罚这么重
for beating up a couple of boys.
他就是骂了我一句  你何必打他
He abused me. Why did you have to beat him'?
你怎么不早说
Now you tell me!
以后你说什么我们都听  妈妈
We'll obey your every command, mummy.
救我们脱离苦海吧
Just save us from this wrestling.
这一年你们就忘了我这个妈吧
For one year forget that you have a mother.
这么快就忘了
Hey! Forgot so quickly?
太荒谬了  马哈维亚
How utterly absurd, Mahavir!
女孩进摔跤场
Girls in the wrestling arena?
你是想让我晚节不保吗
Will you have me sin at this age?
芭比塔
Babita...
你能帮我揉揉腿吗
Will you press my legs please?
我还想让你帮我揉呢
I was going to ask you the same thing.
永远要尊重大地母亲
Always respect Mother Earth.
你给大地的尊重越多
The more you respect it,
能得到的尊重也就越多
the more respect you will get in return.
叔叔成功带吉塔和芭比塔进了摔跤场
Uncle had managed to bring Geeta and Babita to the wrestling pit,
但是还差了点东西
but there was something missing.
为了让吉塔和芭比塔练得更好
In order for Geeta and Babita to train well,
他们需要跟优秀的摔跤手练习
they needed to practice with good wrestlers.
奥姆卡尔
Omkar?
他吗
Him?
对
Yes.
会不会太过分了  兄弟
Isn't that too much, brother?
你让你家闺女们练摔跤已经够离谱了
It was bad enough that you were making the girls wrestle.
现在还让她们跟男孩打
Now you want them to fight boys?
同意还是不同意
Yes or no?
我不想同意
I don't have the heart to say yes.
但我也不敢不同意
And, I don't have the courage to say no.
好  送他过来吧
Okay, then send him over.
你们城门失火  殃及了我这条池鱼
Because of you both I'm caught in the crossfire.
别抱怨了
Stop complaining!
你只是被殃及
You are just caught in the crossfire.
我们可是水深火热
We've been pushed into war.
继续跑
Keep running!
爸爸为什么叫他跟我们训练
Why has papa got him to train with us?
他这小身板毫无挑战力
This pint-sized boy is no challenge.
他就是个假把式
He looks like a 'TTSS' to me.
什么意思
What does that mean?
光说不练啊
Tall on Talk, Short on Strength.
说我假把式  是吧
'TTSS'... is it?
轻点  我可是你妹妹
Go easy, I'm your little sister.
行行行
Yes... yes!
恕我直言
Don't mind me saying,
你们家这俩孩子有点弱呀
but your girls are a little weak.
要不咱俩比比
Want to fight me?
我等会儿再来
I'll be right back.
我不明白你的做法
I don't understand your ways.
我本以为  我可以既当教练又当父亲
At one time, I can either be their coach or their father.
但我给他们当教练
When the coach is at work,
父亲的角色就得退后
the father has to take a backseat.
对不起
Sorry
我不该说你"假把式"
for calling you 'TTSS'.
抱歉  来不及了
Sorry. My foot!
你觉得这是在开玩笑吗
You think this is a joke?
你就这么让他把你摔倒
He is throwing you down and you are letting him?
他从左边进攻的时候
When he attacks from the left,
为什么你不调整重心到左边然后防守
why don't you stabilize yourself on the left and defend?
对不起  爸爸...
Sorry, Papa-
孩子  这是摔跤
Child, this is wrestling,
说上三句对不起这比赛就输了
three sorrys and the game is over.
加油
Come on.
再来
Try again.
你的力量哪儿去了
Where's the strength in you?
你教女儿们摔跤
You are training the girls to wrestle,
我没意见
I didn't say anything.
但我不允许你在我的厨房里煮鸡肉
But I will not allow you to cook chicken in my kitchen!
试着理解一下
Try and understand.
摔跤手要补充蛋白质
Wrestlers require protein.
我不管
I don't care!
如果在我的厨房里煮肉
If meat is cooked in my kitchen,
那我就不吃东西了
I will stop eating.
你要让女儿们做营养不良的摔跤手吗
You want your girls to be weak wrestlers?
我不管
I don't know anything.
反正绝对不允许在我的厨房煮鸡肉
There's no way chicken will be cooked in my kitchen!
-奥姆卡尔  -在
- Omkar! - Yes.
你知道怎么下厨吗
Do you know how to cook?
不知道  叔叔
No, uncle.
那就学
Then learn.
她们现在的饮食我们都快供不起了
We don't have enough money for their current diet.
怎么给她们提供鸡肉
How can we afford chicken now'?
什么  100卢比的鸡肉20卖给你
What? Sell you chicken worth 100 rupees for 20?
我还能从这种交易中获利
And I will benefit from this deal?
你倒是给我解释一下怎么算的
Why don't you explain the math?
听着
Look,
吉塔和芭比塔以后会成为著名摔跤手
Geeta and Babita will eventually become famous wrestlers.
如果大家知道
And when people will find
她们吃的鸡肉是你们店提供的
out that they eat chicken from your shop,
你想他们是不是会从你这儿买更多鸡肉
where do you think they'll buy chicken from?
说得有道理
That makes sense.
但就20卢比
But just 20 rupees?
我可以去找别的店
There are other shops too.
等等...听着
Wait... listen.
40卢比怎么样
Let's make it 40.
最多25卢比  不能再多了
I won't give a dime more than 25.
我煎好洋葱了
I have browned the onions,
这个锅不许再回到我的厨房
and now this pot will not go back in my kitchen.
现在把鸡肉放到锅里
Now, put the chicken in the pot.
然后小火慢炖
And let it cook on a slow flame.
要配米饭吃
It's to be eaten with rice.
好吧...也可以配面包吃
But... it can also be eaten with bread.
叔叔在尽力训练
Uncle was fulfilling his duty,
村民也在尽力说闲话
and the villagers, theirs.
女孩子还是更适合待在厨房
Girls are best suited for the kitchen,
而不是去摔跤
not for wrestling.
马哈维亚·辛格疯了
Mahavir Singh has gone mad.
不是疯了
Not mad,
是不知羞耻
he's become shameless.
他让女孩穿上短裤跟男孩摔跤
He's getting the girls to wear shorts and fight boys.
自从开始摔跤  你们走路就像男人婆
Since you all started wrestling, your walk has become very manly.
真好奇接下来还会发生什么
Wonder what else will happen?
接下来我的拳头会砸到你脸上
Next, it'll be my fist and your face.
要是你生了个男孩就好了
If only you had given birth to a boy!
她们妈妈竟然都不反对
Their mother doesn't protest either.
整个村子的人都在嘲笑我们
The entire village is laughing at us.
谁会娶我们的女儿
Who will marry our girls'?
我会让我的女儿们变得无比优秀
I will make our girls so capable,
那些男生如果不娶她们
that boys will not choose them,
就只能娶其他男生
they will choose boys!
我今天要跟爸爸讲  摔跤学不下去了
I'm going to tell papa today, this wrestling isn't working out.
我也是
Me, too.
男生
B-O-Y... boy.
猫
C-A-T... cat.
爸爸  摔跤学不下去了
Papa, this wrestling isn't working out...
对芭比塔来说
for Babita.
是的  爸爸...而且
Yes, papa... and,
吉塔累得都在课上睡着了
Geeta gets so tired that she falls asleep in class.
她完全不能集中注意力在学习上
She can't concentrate on her studies at all.
芭比塔全身又酸又痛
Babita's body aches terribly.
整晚都翻来覆去睡不着觉
She keeps tossing and turning all night.
在学校女生们都取笑吉塔
In school, girls tease Geeta
说她是个男人婆
by calling her a man.
很可怜  不是吗
Sad, isn't it?
这些都不是问题
None of these seem like a problem.
等有真正的问题再告诉我
Tell me if there is a real problem.
念吧
Read.
大象
E-l-e-p-h-a-n-t
爸爸  老在泥里摔跤
Papa, our hair is getting ruined
我们头发都脏死了
because of wrestling in the mud.
她都长虱子了
She even has lice.
我光今晚就杀了8只虱子
I killed eight this evening.
你看  这才是真正的问题
Now, that's a real problem.
好  明天早上5点做好准备
Okay, be ready tomorrow at 5 AM.
爸爸  拜托
Papa, please.
我们没有任何问题了
We don't have any problem.
事实上  我们很喜欢摔跤
In fact, we are enjoying it.
请不要剪掉我们头发
Please don't cut our hair.
我们会照你说的做
We will do as you say.
妈妈  帮我们劝劝他
Ma, say something.
你看爸爸要做什么
Look what papa is doing.
请不要剪掉我们的头发  爸爸
Please don't cut our hair, papa.
你说什么我们都照做
We'll do whatever you say.
我们会每天早起
We'll wake up in the morning!
什么都做...绝对不抱怨
Do everything... won't ever complain.
只要不剪掉我们的头发  拜托了
Just don't cut our hair, please.
拜托  爸爸
Please, papa.
剪掉
Cut it.
Cut it?
头发长能当饭吃吗
Can you grow it?
那就剪掉
Then cut it.
让她们去摔跤没有关系
Getting them to wrestle was still okay,
但是剪头发有点太残忍了
but it's cruel to chop their hair off!
毕竟她们是女孩子
They are girls, after all.
我做的一切都是为她们好
Whatever I'm doing is for their best.
任何让她们从摔跤上分心的东西
Anything that distracts them from wrestling,
我都会除掉
I will get rid of!
"这是满月呀  还是太阳呢"
"Is that the full moon or the sun!"
真奇怪  它们今天一起冒出来了
I'm confused... today both seem to have risen together.
别理他  芭比塔
Let it go, Babita.
要怪就怪我们的星星
Our stars are to blame.
我受够摔跤了
Enough of wrestling,
是时候反抗了
now, it's time for a street-fight!
在哈里亚纳邦一个叫巴拉里的小镇
And then, in a small village of Haryana called Balali,
一场叛变开始了
a grand rebellion began.
起义者吉塔和芭比塔
Revolutionaries Geeta and Babita
对抗独裁者马哈维亚·辛格
versus dictator Mahavir Singh.
叔叔的兵工厂被一座接一座地摧毁
All of uncle's arsenal were neutralized one by one.
闹钟的时间也被改了
The alarm clock was cleverly misguided.
怎么了  爸爸
What happened, papa?
你今天迟到了
You are late today.
年纪大了
Age is catching up.
没关系
No problem.
我们已经完成了今天的训练
We've finished today's training.
走吧  芭比塔
Come, Babita.
耗费了无数灯泡
Countless light-bulbs were martyred.
怎么每天都会烧坏保险丝
How come the bulb fuses everyday'?
质量不行...爸爸
Quality... papa,
质量不行
quality!
假装受伤
Injury was made an ally.
在场地上假摔然后投降
In the battlefield, surrender was given without a fight.
你是不是欠揍
Should I give it to you?
叔叔虽然有两只手
And uncle, despite having both hands,
但却无助得像电影《复仇的火焰》里
felt helpless like the armless character
无臂主角一样
from the film 'Sholay'.
出去
Get out of here!
我不明白怎么突然之间我就这么强了
I couldn't understand how I had suddenly become so strong.
但叔叔清楚  为什么吉塔和芭比塔
But uncle understood very well why Geeta and Babita,
突然之间变这么弱了
had suddenly become so weak.
吉塔和芭比塔以为她们赢了战争
Geeta and Babita thought that they had won the war.
你们要去桑尼塔的婚礼吗
Are you going to Sunita's wedding?
妈...妈妈
M... mummy.
穿成这样是去给我丢脸吗
Are you trying to embarrass me?
挑一个
Choose one.
这个
This one.
我看看
Let me see.
我女儿终于看起来像女孩子了
Finally, my girls are looking like girls.
别告诉爸爸
Don't tell papa.
8点前要回家
Come home before 8 P.M.
算了  兄弟
Let it go, brother.
他疯了
He is crazy.
我们只错过了一天的训练
We missed training just for a day.
有必要闹得这么凶吗
What was the need to create such a big scene?
怎么会有强迫女儿做摔跤手的爸爸
What kind of father forces his daughters to become wrestlers?
逼她们每天5点起床跑步
Makes them wake up at 5 A.M. to run.
把她们当奴隶一样使唤
Works them like slaves.
让她们跟男孩摔跤
Makes them fight boys.
如果她们反抗  就剪掉她们的头发
And if they protest, he cuts their hair.
愿神不会给其他人这样一个父亲
May God never give anyone such a father.
我倒是希望神能给我一个这样的父亲
I wish God had given me such a father.
至少你们的父亲在乎你们
At least your father thinks about you.
否则  我们的现实就是
Otherwise, our reality is,
一个女孩子从出生开始
the moment a girl is born,
就教她做饭  打扫
teach her to cook and clean,
让她做所有的家务活
make her do all the household chores.
等她长到14岁
And, once she turns 14,
就把她嫁出去
marry her off.
摆脱掉一个"负担"
Get rid of the "Burden"!
把她交给一个
And hand her over to a man,
她从未见过的男人
whom she has never seen before.
让她生孩子并抚养长大
Make her bear children and raise them.
她的一生只能如此
That's all she's good for.
至少你们父亲把你们当作孩子看待
At least your father considers you his child.
他是在和全世界作斗争
He is fighting against the whole world.
他默默忍受着别人的嘲讽
He is silently tolerating their taunts.
为什么
Why?
就是为了你们俩可以有一个未来...
So that the two of you can have a future...
有真正的生活
A life.
他做错什么了
What is he doing wrong?
那一天  我明白了一个事实
That day, one fact became clear to me.
不知道吉塔和芭比塔怎么样
Don't know about Geeta and Babita,
反正我肯定没有摔跤手的血液
but I sure didn't have wrestling in my blood.
看他生气的样子
Look at him sulk.
给他点黄油  妈妈
Give him some butter, ma.
他太弱了
He's become so weak.
我是故意输掉逗你们开心的
I lost intentionally to make you happy.
输就是输  "假把式"
Get lost... 'TTSS'!
还说什么"故意输掉..."
"Lost intentionally..."
别担心
Don't worry.
我们不会传出去
It'll remain between us.
毕竟你是家人
After all, you are family.
你的声誉也是我们的
Your reputation is ours, too.
别这么自大
Don't get so cocky.
明天看我的
Watch me tomorrow.
明天不行
You won't be able to tomorrow.
不  叔叔  明天我一定会尽力的
No, uncle. Tomorrow, I will definitely put up a tough fight.
我们明天要去罗塔克
We are going to Rohtak tomorrow.
参加一场摔跤比赛
For a wrestling competition.
但是  我还没准备好参加摔跤比赛呢
But, I am not ready for a wrestling competition yet.
谁说是你参加了
Who is talking about you?
让她去跟男生摔跤
She will fight boys?
她坚持不了2分钟的  叔叔
She won't last two minutes, uncle.
为什么
Why?
你不就是个男生吗
Aren't you a boy?
她就打败你了
She thrashed you.
我这辈子看过很多场摔跤比赛
I had seen a lot of wrestling competitions in my life.
但今天我将要目睹一场
But today I was going to witness a bout,
哈里亚纳邦前所未见的比赛
the likes of which, had never been seen before in Haryana.
不可避免会引起骚动
A riot was inevitable.
马哈维亚·辛格·珀尕先生...欢迎
Mr. Mahavir Singh Phogat... welcome!
很荣幸您能来观看这场比赛
It's an honor that you have come to watch the competition.
我还带来了一位摔跤手
I've got a wrestler with me too.
叫什么名字
Name, please.
吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
Geeta Kumari Phogat.
什么
What?
吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
Geeta Kumari Phogat.
你让一个女孩来摔跤
You'll make a girl wrestle?
对  怎么了
Yes. So?
写
Write.
先生  如果有天我组织一场厨艺比赛
Sir, the day I organize a cooking competition,
一定邀请吉塔小姐参加
that day get Ms. Geeta along.
但这是摔跤比赛
This is a wrestling competition!
我们大老远过来
We have come from very far.
不会空手而归
We won't return without a fight.
要么让吉塔摔跤
Either Geeta will fight,
要么你跟我摔跤
or you and I.
你简直是在胡言乱语
First, you utter nonsense,
而且还冥顽不灵
and then you are being stubborn too!
你什么意思
What do you mean?
你让一个女孩与男孩摔跤
You want a girl to wrestle with boys?
也许你不在意自己的荣誉  但我们在意
You may not be bothered about your honor, but we are.
我现在就可以让你荣誉扫地
I will have your honor laid out now!
且慢...先生
Please... sir.
且慢...我们非常尊重你  先生
Please... we really respect you, sir.
但是你所要求的事  不可能发生
But what you ask for, can't happen.
我们不能这么做  兄弟
We can't do this, brother.
我们走
Let's go.
他怎么敢...
How dare he...
你有个绝佳的宣传机会
You are getting a chance to play the game,
但是你错过了
and you are giving a walkover?
什么意思
Meaning?
我们举办摔跤比赛几年了
How many years have we been holding wrestling competitions?
五年
Five.
有多少人来看
How many people come to see?
很少
Just a handful.
所以呢
So?
笨蛋  你想想
Dimwit, think about it.
在这镇上从来没人看过女孩子摔跤
In a town that has never seen a girl wrestle,
如果一个女生和一个男生摔跤
when a girl wrestles a boy,
有多少人会来看
how many people will come to watch?
我们比赛的票价会飞涨
Our competition will go through the roof!
可万一那女孩摔断了手或腿怎么办
But what if the girl breaks her arms or legs?
让她断好了
Let them break.
至少你拯救了比赛的危局
You bandage your broken competition.
即使每张票只卖2卢比
Even if you charge two rupees per ticket,
也够你的摔跤手们吃一个月了
your wrestlers will eat for months.
马哈维亚
Mahavir-ji!
女士们先生们  男孩和女孩们
Ladies and gentlemen, boys and girls!
大家肯定见过女孩表演钻火圈或吞蛇
You must have seen a girl walk on fire, eat a snake.
但今天  大家将见证罗塔克史上第一次
But today, for the first time in the history of Rohtak,
女孩与男孩的摔跤比赛
see a girl wrestling a boy in a competition,
比赛将在半小时内开始  地点拉尔广场
in half-an-hour, at Lal Chowk.
票价  2卢比
Tickets - two rupees.
一位女摔跤手  只要2卢比
A wrestling girl for two rupees!
你会赢的
You have to win!
就是把你的选手和头狮子关在一起
Even if you were to pit your boys against a lion,
都不会有这么多人来围观
there still wouldn't have been such a crowd.
你觉得怎么样
What do you think?
她能坚持几秒
How many seconds will she last?
3...3...3...
S... s... s...
兄弟  等不到你说完她就已经倒下了
Mate, by the time you finish she'll be done and dusted.
她会像这样穿着短裤吗
Will she fight in trunks like these?
走开
Get lost!
我好期待啊
I was just hoping.
她在哪儿
Where is she?
她看起来很辣
She looks hot.
希望她的T恤不会撕破
Hope her t-shirt doesn't tear.
我倒是希望会撕破
I hope it does!
加油  吉塔
Go, Geeta!
她爸爸简直是疯了
Her father has lost it!
你知道泥地摔跤的规则吗
Do you know the rules of mud-wrestling?
那就挑对手吧  你想输给谁
Then choose who you want to lose to.
你们觉得她会选谁
Who do you think she'll pick?
我们的骨感小蜘蛛
Our Scrawny Spider.
那他终于能赢一次了
He will win for the first time.
天啊  贾西会打得她找不着北
Gosh, Jassi will beat her to pulp!
你们三个  站到那边去
Three of you, out of here.
你女儿输定了
Your girl has lost it.
趁还有时间  快阻止她
There is still time, stop her.
不然你得用担架把她抬回去
Or she'll go back on a stretcher.
在击败对手之前你要先战胜恐惧
Before you fight a bout you have to fight fear.
至少我女儿已经战胜了恐惧
At least, my girl has conquered fear.
别太认真  她是个姑娘
Go easy, she's a girl.
你最好别这么想
Don't make that mistake.
你要让我们难堪吗
Will you embarrass us?
吉塔  漂亮
Geeta, great going!
她输定了
She's gone.
不...不错的反击
Wh... wh... what a save!
你打得很好
You fought well.
非常好
Excellent!
组委会奖励获胜者贾西
The committee awards the winning wrestler, Jassi,
20卢比的现金
with a cash prize of 20 rupees.
我们的赞助人卡塔·赛
And from our patron, Kartar Singh,
特别奖励吉塔·库马莉50卢比
a special prize for Geeta Kumari of 50 rupees!
对不起  爸爸...
Sorry, Papa-
没关系
It's okay.
我们走
Come on.
你真走运  不然你得躺在担架上回去
You got lucky, or you'd have gone home on a stretcher.
爸爸
Papa,
下一次比赛是什么时候
when is the next fight?
从明天起你也要为她祈祷
From tomorrow you'll have to bless her as well.
人们再一次开始谈论吉塔和芭比塔
Once again people had started talking about Geeta and Babita.
这两个来自巴拉里的女孩能和男孩摔跤
These two girls come from Balali and thrash boys.
这家伙输给了一个女孩
This fellow lost to a girl.
你倒是自己上去试试
Why don't you fight her'?
但这一次掌声取代了责问
But this time the heckles were replaced with applause!
有些人不想和女孩子摔跤
Some did not want to wrestle with the girls.
有些则不允许她们摔跤
And some didn't allow them to wrestle.
请离开
Please leave!
吉塔和芭比塔不仅赢得了比赛
Geeta and Babita were winning not just wrestling competitions,
还赢得了观众的心
but hearts, too.
14900  15000  15100
14,900... 15,000... 15,150.
你们是高级摔跤手了
You've become a senior wrestler!
由于被哈里亚纳邦州队选中
By getting selected to the Haryana state team,
吉塔·库马莉不仅为学校带来了荣誉
Geeta Kumari has brought fame not only to our school,
也为整个波瓦尼地区带来了荣耀
but to the entire district of Bhiwani.
我们相信
And we are sure that,
她将在初级国家比赛再次整得荣誉
she will make our town proud in the National Sub-Juniors, too.
请假  还要两个月
Leave? For two months?
你女儿结婚了吗
Is your daughter getting married?
我要帮吉塔准备全国大赛  先生
I have to prepare Geeta for the Nationals, sir.
算了吧
Forget about it.
如果她是结婚  我还能考虑你的申请
If she was getting married, I might have considered.
我无法理解你的决定
I don't understand your decisions.
我没有选择
I didn't have a choice.
我不能放弃我的梦想
I couldn't let go of my dream,
所以我选择放弃工作
so, I let go of the job.
你准备做什么
What will you do now?
我会开始种咱们家的地
I'll start farming on our own plot of land.
这很困难
It's hard work,
但至少我有时间训练女儿了
but at least I will be able to give the girls time.
提图  把这个放车里
Titu... put this in the car.
等一下  好了
Wait... go...
马哈维亚·辛格  你说什么
Yes, Mahavir Singh-ji, what were you saying?
如果我能获得些资金  将大有帮助
If I could get some funds, it would help a lot.
我的女儿已经达到了邦级水平
My girl has now reached the state level.
所以...
So...
达到邦级水平有什么了不起
What is the big deal in reaching state level?
还是女子摔跤
That too in ladies wrestling?
你倒是第一个为了女儿独自跑来的
Your daughter ran alone, and came first.
你要资金做什么
What do you need the funds for?
先生  我想给她买一块垫子来训练
Sir, I want to buy a mat for her to train on.
她打得很好
She's playing well.
如果你今天资助她
If you support her today,
有一天  她会令整个国家骄傲
then one day, she will make the nation proud.
听着  马哈维亚·辛格
Look, Mahavir Singh-ji,
我们在体育上的资金总共有这么多
we get this much funding for sports.
而分给摔跤的有这么多
Wrestling gets this much.
去掉男子摔跤
Keep aside gents wrestling,
再刨除教练  伙食  交通  器材
then remove coaching, dieting, traveling, equipment, etc.
给女子摔跤的资金只有这么多
All that remains for ladies wrestling is this much.
为了这么点钱  你还给我买了盒甜点
And for this much, you bought me a box of sweets.
不过我们完全支持你
But you have our complete support.
印度赢不了金牌的原因
The reason India doesn't win medals,
就是因为你这样的官员尸位素餐
is because officers like you are warming these seats.
好吧  那我不做了
Alright. I'll get up.
提图  给我拿午饭来
Titu, serve me lunch.
马哈维亚·辛格  要一起吃吗
Mahavir Singh-ji, care to join me for lunch?
联邦就是这些蛀虫的温床
The Federation is a breeding ground for such termites.
他们毁掉了体育
They have ruined sports.
他们不给运动员资助
There is no support for sports persons,
输了他们还笑话你
only abuses when you don't win.
金牌运动员可不是从树上长出来的
Medalists don't grow on trees.
你要培育他们
You have to nurture them.
用爱  努力  激情培育
With love, with hard work, with passion.
而这帮坏人却连买块垫子的钱都不出
And here, the scoundrels don't give money for even a mat.
什么垫子  老兄
What is a mat, brother?
摔跤手用的合成垫
Synthetic mattresses on which wrestlers fight.
那不就是床垫吗
A mattress is a mattress!
不是吗
No?
我说错什么了吗
Did I say something wrong?
叔叔一直搅得我们夜不能寐  这是比喻
Uncle had already ruined our sleep, figuratively speaking.
而现在他是真的这么做了
Now he was hell bent on doing it literally, too.
在垫子上摔跤和在泥地里摔跤不同
Wrestling on a mat is different from mud-wrestling.
现在我们要开始在垫子上摔跤
Now we have to wrestle on the mat.
在垫子上摔跤你要尽可能拿分
And in mat-wrestling you have to score points.
你可能拿到一分  两分  三分或五分
You can score one, two, three or five points.
奥姆卡尔
Omkar...
如果你抱住对手的腰
If you hold the opponent by the waist,
并让他膝盖着地
and drop him to his knees,
你可以得一分
then you score one point.
着地时若能让对手背部着地
And from the ground position if you roll him on to his back,
则得两分
then you score two points.
有许多方法可以做到这点
There are different ways to do this.
叔叔
Uncle!
比如这样
Like this.
或是着地时这样做
Or from the ground position, like this!
如果你以站立的姿势让对手背部着地
If you flip your opponent on his back from a standing position,
你就能得三分
then you will score three points.
不要  叔叔
Please, uncle!
像这样  三分
Like this... three points.
像这样  以站姿  让他背部着地
Like this... from standing position... on to his back.
想拿五分很难  但不是不可能
To score five points is difficult, but it can be done.
如果你以站立的姿势
If you flip your opponent from a standing position,
将你的对手像彩虹一样掀翻
above your head in a rainbow-like arc,
并使他背部着地
and have him fall on his back,
你就可以得五分
then you score five points!
看好了
Watch.
不  不  求你了叔叔
No... no, please, uncle!
-过来  -不  求你了
- Come here. - No, please.
真正的摔跤垫和这个不一样
A real wrestling mat is not like this.
而是像这样
It's like this.
运动员要在黄色区域比赛
We have to fight in the yellow area.
红色则是危险区
The red zone is a danger area.
如果你出界  会扣一分
If you step out of it, you lose a point.
每轮两分钟  总共比三轮
There are three rounds of two minutes each.
Three rounds of two minutes each.
赢得其中两轮即获胜
Whoever wins two out of three rounds, wins the match.
先生  你女儿体重不达标
Sir, your daughter is underweight.
所以
So?
听我的  回去吧
Take my advice. Go back.
好好喂她
Feed her,
把她养胖  明年再来
fatten her and come back next year.
如果她这样上场  会骨折的
If she fights like this, she will break her bones.
你就告诉我她能不能上场摔跤
You just tell me whether she is allowed to wrestle or not.
可以
Yes... she is.
签字
Sign up.
国家初级青年大赛
"Sub-Junior Nationals"
漂亮
Good move!
吉塔曾战胜过壮如牛的男孩
Geeta had defeated beefy boys,
这些女孩能撑多久
how long could these girls survive?
那是姑娘还是风暴
Is that a girl or a storm?
国家初级青年大赛冠军
"Sub-Junior National Champion"
国家青年大赛
"Junior Nationals"
她是不是体重不达标
Is she underweight?
是  不过那又怎样
Yes... but how does it matter?
国家青年大赛冠军
"Junior National Champion"
时光飞逝
Time flew by.
吉塔从青年步入成年
Geeta went from junior to senior.
而叔叔
And uncle,
则从中年步入老年
from senior to senior-citizen.
冲啊吉塔
Go... Geeta!
芭比塔和我也已经长大成人
Babita and I, went from shorts to full length pants!
推她  把她推到
Push... push her down!
从侧面摔
Side throw!
哈里亚纳邦万岁
Victory to Haryana!
全国冠军
"National Champion"
叔叔终于梦想成真了
Finally uncle's dream has been achieved.
我们可以松口气了
Now we can all relax.
不
No.
我的梦想还没有成真
My dream remains to be fulfilled.
每年都会有全国冠军
Every year sees a National champion.
只有当你为国家
My dream will be fulfilled,
而非只为自己赢得金牌
when you win gold, not for yourself,
我的梦想才算成真
but for your country.
你今天可以庆祝
You can celebrate today.
但从明天开始你必须为以后做准备
From tomorrow we start preparing further.
爸爸
Papa...
我想和你谈谈
Need to speak to you.
说吧
Tell me.
爸爸
Papa,
因为我是全国冠军  所以...
now that I am a National champion, so...
所以什么
So?
不  我的意思是
No, I mean,
所有的全国冠军都要去帕蒂亚拉
all National champions need to go to Patiala,
接受之后的训练
for further training.
在国家体育学院
To the National Sports Academy.
你想说什么
What are you getting at'?
直说
Tell me clearly.
我也得去  爸爸
I will have to go too, papa.
从现在起  我要去那里训练了
From now, I'll have to train there,
接受国家教练的指导
under the national coach.
吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
Geeta Kumari Phogat.
摔跤
Wrestling.
这地方看起来真棒
The place looks good.
希望教练也不错
Let's hope the coach is good too.
姑娘们  过来
Girls, come on.
你们应该感到高兴
You all must be rejoicing,
因为你们即将接受先进的训练
at the thought of advanced training.
忘记学习
Well, forget about learning,
你们首先要学会的就是遗忘
first you have to learn to forget!
忘记你们接受的错误的训练
Forget the wrong training you've received.
错误的饮食  错误的练习和技巧
Wrong diet, wrong exercise, wrong technique.
忘掉这一切之后
And after forgetting all that,
你们真正的训练才开始
your real training will begin,
我是国家教练  珀麦德·提丹
with National Coach, Pramod Kadam.
你们只能学习我教给你们的
And you will only learn what I teach you.
-明白了吗  -明白
- Is that clear? - Yes, sir!
很好
Good.
热身
Warm up.
给我茶
Get me tea!
动起来  姑娘们
Come on, girls.
能量  充满能量
Energy... more energy!
没错  就是这样
Yes, that's the way.
保持住
Keep it UP!
很好
Good.
打扰了  先生
Namaste, sir.
先生  我是马哈维亚·辛格·珀尕
Sir, I'm Mahavir Singh Phogat.
吉塔的爸爸
Geeta's father.
好的
Okay.
之前就是我训练她的
I'm the one who has trained her.
很好
Yes... good.
她很棒
She's good.
很强壮  耐力好
Very strong, with a lot of stamina.
我的茶呢
Where's my tea?
快  动起来
Come on... move it!
先生  我有一个请求
Sir... one request.
如果吉塔能接受正确的指导
If Geeta gets the right coaching,
她无疑能在国际赛事中拿到奖牌
she will definitely win an international medal.
吉塔
Geeta!
大腿和小腿之间应该呈90度
There should be a 9O degree angle between your calf and thigh.
这都是谁教你的
Who has taught you?
你这样怎么赢国际奖牌
Is this how you will win an international medal?
你是来送她的对吧
You came to drop her, right?
你的任务已经完成了
You've done that.
剩下的交给我吧
Now leave the rest to me.
别浪费我的时间
Don't waste my time!
吉塔高兴吗
Is Geeta happy?
那个学院一定非常大  对吧
The institute must be very big, isn't it?
那里的每个人都是冠军吗
Everyone there must be a champion, isn't it?
所有的器材都棒极了是不是
And the facilities there must be amazing, right?
你今天训练了吗
Have you trained today?
训练了  教练也是顶级的吗
Yes. And the coach must be top notch?
你看起来很想去呀
You seem very eager to go there.
记着  现在我是你的教练
Remember, I'm still your coach.
第一次离开家吗
Your first time away from home?
等着吧  我们会玩得开心的
Just you wait... we'll have a blast.
姑娘们  电视上在演《勇夺芳心》
Girls, 'DDLJ' is showing on TV.
我们一起看吧
Let's watch.
我要睡觉了
I'm going to sleep.
你怎么能拒绝沙鲁克·汗呢
You can't say no to Shah Rukh Khan.
这可是犯罪
It's a sin.
过来
Come.
"拉杰  如果这女孩爱你她会转头"
"Raj, if this girl loves you, she will turn to look at you."
请转头吧
Please turn.
转头
"Turn."
Turn.
转头
"Turn."
她转了
She turned!
留长头发  你会大杀四方的
Just grow your hair. You will kill it.
犀牛使用蛮力
A rhino uses strength,
而老虎会将力量与技术结合
but the tiger uses both strength and technique.
要做老虎  不要做犀牛
Be a tiger, not a rhino.
明白了吗
Clear?
晚上要不要出去
Shall we go out later tonight?
只吃一个没关系的
Just one won't make a difference.
没错  就是这样
Yes, that's the way!
记住  一个小错误就能让你失去金牌
Remember one mistake can cost you the medal.
好的爸爸  训练一切顺利
Yes papa, training is going well.
我要走了  教练在等我
I'm going. Coach-sir is waiting.
再见
Bye!
吉塔
Geeta!
过来
Come here.
忘记你爸爸教给你的技巧
Forget your papa's technique.
只学我教你的东西
Learn only what I teach you.
明白了吗
Got that?
你好
Hello!
抱歉  吉塔出去了
Sorry, Geeta has gone out.
这些年我都是故意输给你们姐妹的
For years I have been losing to both of you intentionally.
真的
It is the truth!
就是这样  看到没
That's it! You see?
摔跤手只有在技巧正确时才会出彩
Wrestlers shine only when the technique is right.
快赢下全国大赛
Win the Nationals soon.
这样你也能来了
You too will be sorted.
好  你什么时候回来
Yes... when are you coming home?
我下周就回
I'm coming next week.
需要什么东西吗
Need something?
不用  你回来就好了
Nothing. You get here.
好的
Okay.
喜欢吗
Did you like it?
真的吗
Really?
你头发长了
You grew out your hair.
挺好看的
It's looking good.
你爸可不会喜欢
Your papa won't like it.
不能再按照爸爸那一套了
Now everything can't work the way papa wants.
教练都没说什么
Coach-sir didn't say anything.
而且他是个出色的教练
And he is such an accomplished coach.
你在那边随心所欲
You do as you please over there.
回来了可得收敛点
Just be a little careful here.
妈妈
Mummy.
真正的训练应该是自由的
Real training happens with a lot of freedom.
根本没这么多限制
Not with so many restrictions.
我们看电影  看电视  去外面吃东西
We watch movies, television, eat out, too.
我照样表现很好
My performance hasn't suffered.
我现在是国家体育学院顶级摔跤手
I am the topmost wrestler at the NSA.
回来了啊  摔跤手
You home, wrestler?
-怎么样啊  -挺好的  爸爸
- How are you? - I am fine, papa.
训练的如何
How's your training going?
她马上要去悉尼参加比赛了
She's going to Sydney for a fight.
训练怎么样了
How's your training going?
进展顺利  爸爸
It's going very well, papa.
你知道的...
You've seen...
我学了许多新的东西
I'm learning a lot of new things.
新的策略  动作  技巧...
New strategy, moves, technique...
很棒
very good.
我觉得我也可以教她几招
I have thought that I will teach her some things, too.
要知道她也是要拿下全国冠军的人
After all, she too has to win the Nationals.
头发长了啊
You've grown your hair.
-爸爸... -没事
- Papa... - No.
挺好的
It's good.
别光想着进攻  还得防守
Don't just attack, you've to defend, too.
抱住我
Hold me.
现在你要怎么挣脱
Now, how will you free yourself?
像这样握住  挣脱  然后攻击
Hold this way, break and attack.
懂了吗
Got that?
那已经是老一套了
That's an old technique.
让我来...
Let me...
抱住我
Hold me.
抱紧点
Tight.
用你的大拇指像这样抓住
Push your thumbs in this way,
移动到一边
and move it to the side.
不是前面  而是侧边  挣脱  进攻
Not in the front... but to the side. Break and attack.
我的技巧怎么了
What's wrong with my technique?
有什么问题吗
What's wrong?
不是的  爸爸  没什么问题
No, papa. It's not wrong.
只是这样更准确  这是教练教的
This is more correct. Coach-sir has taught it.
这么说你现在是专家了
So now you are an expert?
国际级别的
International?
爸爸  我只是...
Papa, I was...
我倒想看看你教练都教了你些什么
I'd like to know, what is it that your coach-sir has taught you,
你爸爸教不了的
that your father couldn't.
不是教她  我来
Not her, show me.
来吧
Come on.
用大拇指像这样抓住...
Push your thumbs in this way...
这就是你那教练教你的吗
So, this is what your coach-sir has taught you!
你准备就这样拿国际冠军吗
Is this how you'll win an international medal?
我刚才没准备好  爸爸
I wasn't ready, papa.
那就做好准备
So, get ready.
这就是我学到的  爸爸
This is what I was saying, papa.
看到不一样的了吗
Isn't there a difference?
今天的事你有点过了
What happened today wasn't right.
哪里过了
What wasn't right?
这是必然的结果
This was bound to happen.
总得有人告诉爸爸他的技巧太弱了
Someone had to tell papa that his techniques are weak.
不是他的技巧太弱
His techniques aren't weak.
是他的身体越来越弱了
He's become a little weak.
别忘了你也是靠爸爸"很弱"的技巧
And don't forget that you've won the Nationals,
才拿下全国冠军的
based on his "weak" techniques.
你能靠这些技巧拿下全国冠军  芭比塔
You can win the Nationals with these techniques, Babita,
但是打不赢国际比赛
not international matches.
越早明白这点越好
And the sooner you realize this, the better.
那好吧
Alright.
你坚持你的技巧
You keep faith in your techniques.
我还是相信爸爸教的
I still put my faith in papa.
我会向上天祈祷你赢得全国大赛的
I pray to God that you fight well at the Nationals.
我也祈祷你在国际比赛中能有好成绩
And I pray that you do well in your international tournament.
"世界锦标赛  悉尼"
"World Championship, Sydney"
全国大赛  新德里
"National Games, New Delhi"
冲啊  芭比塔
Go... Babita!
把她摔出去
Throw her.
吉塔 你怎么回事
What are you doing, Geeta?
你在搞什么  吉塔
防守啊
Defend!
进攻
Attack!
漂亮
Good one!
你怎么防守的
Is this how you defend?
下一轮也打进攻
The next round, too, play attacking.
你好像不开心  爸爸
You don't look happy, papa.
我表现得不好吗
Didn't I fight properly?
你很棒  宝贝
No, my dear.
你表现得和我期待中一样好
You fought exactly as I expected.
只是没想到吉塔能有打进国际这天
But, I never imagined Geeta would fight like this.
现在你也拿下全国冠军了
And now, you too, have won the Nationals.
也要去国家体育学院
You too, will go to NSA.
会有一个新的教练
You'll have a new coach.
而爸爸已经越来越老了
And your papa once again will become old.
爸爸
Papa.
永远记住
Never forget,
你是如何走到这一步的
how you got till here.
好啊  冠军
Hey, champion.
姐姐
Hello, sis.
还在生气吗
Still upset?
来
Come.
-你包里都装了些什么  -我来拿吧
- What did you fill in the bag? - Let me get it.
太沉了
It's so heavy.
嗨  加斯密特
Hi, Jasmeet!
这是我妹妹  芭比塔
This is my younger sister, Babita.
一家子摔跤手哦
Whoa! A family of wrestlers!
这是食堂
Here is the mess.
大家都抢着吃饭
This is where we hog.
这儿是休息室
This is the lounge.
我们在这娱乐  看看电视
Here we chill and watch TV.
训练中心在哪
Where is the training center?
你可真着急
My, aren't you eager!
明天再去看  今天先休息
See it tomorrow. Rest today.
我能说两句吗
Can I say something?
恕我冒犯
Don't feel offended.
说吧
Tell me.
你变了很多
You've changed a lot.
我还记得你第一次输掉比赛
I remember the first time you lost a match.
一整晚都没睡着
You couldn't sleep all night.
可现在  即使输了国际比赛你也...
And now, in spite of losing an international fight you are...
我是说  你似乎完全无动于衷
I mean, it doesn't show at all on your face.
是老爸教你说的这些吗
Has papa trained you to say this?
爸爸教的技巧我记得非常清楚
I remember papa's training very well.
但你好像都忘了
It seems you've forgotten.
你管自己好好训练就行了
You focus on your training.
我自己能搞定
I will manage mine.
还有  用得着这样教训我吗
And why are you lecturing me?
只不过输了一场比赛而已
I've only lost one match.
"莫斯科"
"Moscow"
第二回合吉塔·库马莉仍然落后
Geeta Kumari is trailing in the second round as well.
她打得不错  但进展甚微
She's fought well, but hasn't managed much.
吉塔试图反击
Geeta tries,
卡沙得到1分
but Kasha scores one point.
比赛结束
And that's it!
吉塔·库马莉率先在这届锦标赛中淘汰
Geeta Kumari makes an early exit from the world championship.
非常遗憾
What a disappointment!
吉塔·库马莉·珀尕又一次战败
Yet another defeat for India's Geeta Kumari Phogat.
在雅加达锦标赛中  吉塔第一轮被淘汰
In Jakarta too, Geeta exits in the first round.
伊斯坦布尔世界锦标赛中
A humiliating defeat for
吉塔耻辱战败
Geeta in the Istanbul World Championship!
吉塔  别灰心
Geeta, don't lose hope.
我们已经很努力了  你表现得并不差
We've worked very hard. And you played well.
只是没赢而已
You just couldn't win.
并不意味着你是个糟糕的摔跤手
It doesn't mean you are a bad wrestler.
这是常有的事
It happens.
不是所有人都能打赢国际比赛
Some people are not made for international victory.
你是不是也这么认为
Do you feel too,
我根本不是打赢国际比赛的料
that I'm not cut out for an international medal?
我不知道
I don't know about that.
我只知道
All I know,
你是那个能把男孩子
is that you are the girl,
一跤摔倒在地的女孩
who thrashed boys in mud-wrestling.
你是那个即使体重不达标
You are the girl,
也赢遍了初级国家赛的女孩
who in spite of being underweight, won sub-juniors.
你连续三年拿下全国赛冠军
You beat everyone at the Nationals for three straight years.
如果你不是去国际比赛拿奖牌的料
If you are not cut out for international victory,
那我不知道印度还有哪个女孩是这块料
then I don't know which girl in India is.
我对你有信心
I have a lot of faith in you,
但要知道爸爸比任何人都要相信你
but it's nothing compared to the faith that papa has in you.
再和他谈谈
Talk to him once.
我有什么颜面见他
How do I face him?
他是我们的爸爸
He's our papa.
能糟糕到哪去
At worst, what will happen?
最多骂你一顿
He will give you an earful.
乖乖听着
Take it.
他的教训对我们总是挺有用的
His reprimands have always helped us, haven't they?
吃药吧
Your medicine.
我和芭比塔聊过了
I spoke to Babita.
她说训练进展顺利
She said the training was going well.
还有呢
And?
吉塔状态不好
Geeta is not okay.
请再和她谈谈
Please talk to her once.
你好
Hello.
吉塔
Geeta?
好的  等等
Okay, wait.
是吉塔...
Geeta...
对不起  爸爸
Sorry, Papa.
距离第十九届英联邦运动会还有六个月
Only six months remain for the 19th Commonwealth Games,
这是在印度举行最盛大的运动赛事
the biggest sporting event in India.
印度选手将如何迎战世界优秀运动员
What remains to be seen is how the Indian players hold up,
我们拭目以待
against the world's best.
这次英联邦运动会我希望能得三块奖牌
This time in the Commonwealth games, I want three medals.
不管你们当中谁拿到这三块奖牌
Now, whether they come from you three,
你们仨  或是你们
you three or you three!
我都不管
I don't care.
还剩六个月
There are six months left.
大家全力以赴
Give your best.
明白了吗
Got that?
动起来
Get cracking!
吉塔
Geeta.
过来一下
Come here.
你得拿一块奖牌
You will get one medal.
好的  教练
Yes, sir.
不从之前你输掉的级别里拿
Not in the category that you are losing in,
去打你能赢的级别
but in the category in which you can win.
懂了吗
Got me?
五十五公斤级别对你来说太难了
It's difficult for you to survive in the 55-kilo category.
你现在必须意识到这点
You too must have realised that by now.
在五十一公斤级别里
In the 51-kilo category,
你会比较有把握  或许能赢
you can hold your own, and maybe win.
严格监管每个人的饮食
Monitor everyone's diet strictly.
-别搞砸了  -教练
- No mess ups. - Sir!
教练  我想参加五十五公斤级组
Sir, I want to fight in the 55-kilo category!
你去打五十五公斤级是不会晋级的
If you fight in the 55-kilo category you'll get no where!
她要减掉四公斤
She has to lose four kilos.
调整她的饮食
Change her diet.
从明天开始你训练五十一公斤级的比赛
From tomorrow we'll start your training for the 51-kilo category.
来吧  姑娘们
Come on, girls.
为什么赢不了五十五公斤级比赛
Why won't you win in the 55-kilo category?
你没必要减重
No need for you to lose weight!
你要参加五十五公斤级比赛  一样获胜
You will fight in the 55-kilo category, and win!
我这就去帕蒂亚拉
I'm coming to Patiala.
我们在帕蒂亚拉没有认识的人
We don't know anyone in Patiala.
你去哪里住六个月呢
How will you stay for six months?
租房
On rent.
吃什么呢
And food?
我自己做饭
I'll cook.
我来做饭吧  叔叔
I'll cook, uncle!
我觉得我可以和你一起去
I was thinking that I too could come along.
你去干吗
What will you do there?
以前和我一起训练时她们都表现出色
Well, in the past they did well when they trained with me.
如果她们将来也能和我一起训练...
So, if they train with me in the future too...
老实说  我觉得我是她们的幸运符
Honestly, I think I am their good luck charm.
我是认真的
I mean... that's what I think.
我还能帮你买菜  切菜
And, I will buy vegetables for you, chop them for you,
帮你跑腿  给你按摩
run errands for you, press your feet.
保证你轻松无压力
I'll make sure you are stress-free.
这可是英联邦运动会
You see... it's the Commonwealth Games.
我们必须好好把握
We can't take any chances.
准备拿金牌吧
Start preparing for gold!
"帕蒂亚拉"
"Patiala"
房间在顶楼
The room is on top.
来吧
Come.
这价钱是租不到其他房子了吗
Is there no other room, in the same budget?
挺不错的
It's nice.
确实
Yes!
是挺不错的
It's nice, indeed.
不得不承认
I have to admit!
印度国家体育学院
找谁
Yes?
吉塔跟芭比塔·库玛的父亲和表哥
Geeta and Babita Kumari's father and close cousin.
太酷了
Holy cow!
叔叔  这个地方也太棒了吧
Uncle, doesn't this place seem lovely?
你还好吗  冠军
How are you, champ?
你呢
And you?
挺好的  爸爸
I'm good, Papa.
你怎么来了
Why are you here?
叔叔坚持要我来
Uncle insisted that I come.
说这是英联邦运动会  要好好把握
He said it's the Commonwealth Games. We can't take a chance.
闭嘴  假把式
Shut up, 'TTSS'!
吉塔已经开始五十一公斤级训练了
Geeta's 51-kilo category training has started,
饮食也被控制了
and the diet too.
你继续照这边的饮食和训练来
You continue their diet and training,
剩下的我来处理
I'll supplement the rest.
你们训练几点开始
What time does your training start?
早上七点
7 A.M.
好的
Okay.
明天早上五点做好准备
Be ready at 5 A.M. tomorrow.
停...暂停
Stop... stop.
直接进攻是没用的
Straight attacks won't do.
要学会和对手打心理战
You have to play with the opponent's mind.
做个假动作  声东击西
Fake a move... but make another.
教练  我已经控制她的饮食了
Sir, I had put her on a diet,
不知道为什么体重还是减不下来
but, I don't know why it hasn't reduced.
你最近干吗去了  吉塔
What have you been up to, Geeta?
说话啊  你只会哭吗
Will you say something or just keep crying?
先生  鉴于她们的行为
Sir, judging by their actions
我认为已经没有必要留在体院了
I feel they don't need NSA.
剩下的由你们决定
The rest is up to you.
你们还有什么想说的吗
Do you all have anything to say?
那么你们承认是自己错了
So you admit you are at fault.
先生  她们只有一个错误
Sir, they have just one fault.
就是有个疯狂的父亲
That their father is crazy.
他太热衷于为国家夺得一枚金牌
He is so crazy about getting a gold for the country,
在她们的童年  夺走她们的玩具
that in their childhood itself he snatched away their toys,
强迫她们去摔跤
and made them wrestle.
她们抵抗的时候  剪掉了她们的头发
When they resisted, he cut their hair off.
一味塑造她们成为摔跤手
In order to prepare them,
把她们变得像男孩子一样
he made them wrestle boys.
承受全村人的冷嘲热讽
Took the taunts and abuses of the entire village,
只为有一天她们能为国争光
just so that one day they would make the country proud.
先生  请看
Look, sir.
你看
Look.
这是她在罗塔克赢的五十卢比
These 50 rupees she won at Rohtak.
这是在希萨尔赢的
This in Hisar.
这个来自昌迪加尔
This in Chandigarh.
还有这个...这些都是  先生
This... this, all this... sir.
两个姑娘一路艰辛才走到这里  先生
These girls have traveled a long way to reach here, sir.
请不要让她们现在回去
Now don't tell them to turn back.
这都是我的错
It's all my fault.
我真诚地道歉
I humbly apologise.
教练先生只关心能不能得到三枚奖牌
Coach-sir is just concerned with getting three medals.
不在乎它们也许只是铜牌
No matter if they are bronze.
但我希望  能让国家获得一枚金牌
But I want our country to win gold.
这个女孩能做到的  先生
And this girl can do it, sir.
你们所有人  请在外面稍后
All of you, please wait outside.
你这是在浪费时间
You've made a mistake by wasting time.
参加五十五公斤级吉塔都没法晋级
In 55-kilos, Geeta won't even get selected for India.
要是五十一公斤级  或许还能拿个奖牌
If she had fought in the 51-kilos she could've won a medal.
她本来早就能得五十五公斤级的奖牌
She should've won a medal much earlier, in 55-kilos itself.
都是你的责任
You are responsible for that!
我哪里做错了
What did I do wrong?
吉塔天生擅长进攻
Geeta's natural game is attacking.
你将技巧置于本能之上  抹杀了她的天性
By putting technique above instinct, you've changed her game.
就像叫老虎像大象一样战斗
It's like telling a tiger to fight like an elephant.
最后弄得不伦不类
You'll be left with neither a tiger nor an elephant.
那不如你给我讲讲
So, why don't you tell me,
怎样才能赢得一枚奖牌
how to fight to win a medal!
只要你同意
With your permission,
我愿意现在就地给你展示一下
I would like to demonstrate it here and now.
他们让你们进去
They're calling you inside.
之前的事很不好
What happened was wrong.
但委员会决定再给她们一次机会
But the committee has decided to give them another chance.
谢谢你们  先生们
Thank you, sir.
但是从今天起
But, from today,
既不允许你再进入体院的场地
neither are you allowed to enter the NSA premises,
也不允许她们出去
nor are they allowed to step out.
好的  先生
Okay, sir.
今天  也给我倒一杯吧  叔叔
Today, make one for me too, uncle.
抱歉
Sorry.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们本来是想当主角
We had come to play the lead role,
体院却让我们客串
NSA made ours a guest appearance.
我们还是回家去吧
Let's head back now.
不  奥姆卡尔
No, Omkar.
他们可以阻止我进去
They can stop me from going inside,
但是没人能阻止我执教吉塔
but no one can stop me from coaching Geeta.
干杯  叔叔
Cheers, uncle.
面对她们三个  我都能坚持
Against three of them I held my own.
但是有一个总能把我打倒在地
But the one who took me to the cleaners...
她个头比我小  也没那么强壮
she was smaller than me and not that strong either.
你有那场比赛的录像吗
Do you have a recording of this match?
是的  爸爸  图书馆有
Yes papa, in the library.
复制一份送来给我
Courier me a copy of all.
离德里英联邦运动会只剩三个月了
Only three months remain for the Delhi Commonwealth Games.
在帕蒂亚拉的民族体育学院
And the fervor can be sensed
已经能感受到高涨的热情
at the National Sports Academy in Patiala.
我们去哪里  叔叔
Where are we going, uncle?
叔叔有一点让我很不喜欢
The one thing I disliked about uncle,
就是他总是留悬念
was his constant air of suspense.
简直是要命
It could kill you!
疯狂熟女网站
"CrazyCougar.Com"
欲求不满的姨妈
"The Lustful Aunt"
你要想看电影  去阿马尔影院就好
If you want to watch a movie, let's go to Amar Mahal.
这里放的都是些不正经的片子
They don't show decent films here.
下车
Get off.
狂野的女儿
"Wild Daughter"
有事吗
Yes?
包场多少钱
How much for all the tickets of the next show?
你想看什么
Which film do you want to watch?
我们自带的
We've brought it with us.
暂停
Pause.
继续...
Play-
你们看完了吗
Are you done?
今天你发了...
Be happy-
下一场我们继续包场
Your next show is sold-out too.
你们在干什么呢
What are you guys up to?
我是说  你们带的片子从哪里来的
I mean, where is the movie from?
亚特兰大  印尼
Atlanta... Indonesia.
-进口的  -是的
- Imported? - Yes.
我能拷贝一份吗
Listen, can I make a copy?
我给你们优惠50卢比
Give me 50 rupees less.
她那样打怎么可能赢
How will she win if she fights like this?
叔叔
Uncle!
叔叔  你是收集好信息了
Uncle, you've gathered the knowledge,
但要怎么传进去呢
but how will you pass it on?
体院可是对你下了限制令的
NSA has issued a 'shoot-at-sight' order against you.
上来
Sit.
又是悬念
Again... suspense!
你就是这样摔跤的
Is this how you fight?
像一只发抖的猫咪
Like a quivering kitten?
你要这样摔跤  还不如不摔
If this is how you want to fight, then don't.
怎么了  爸爸
What happened, papa?
我看了你所有的比赛
I saw all your matches.
你那根本不叫摔跤
You weren't wrestling, that's for sure!
你给我的DVD你自己有备份吗
Do you have copies of the DVDs that you gave me?
有  爸爸
Yes, papa.
你能单独观看吗
Can you arrange to watch them alone?
我可以去借一台手提电脑
I'll borrow a laptop.
很好
Alright.
明早五点准备好
Be ready at 5 A.M. tomorrow.
好久没听到爸爸的训斥了
It's been a while since papa gave me an earful.
感觉还不错
Felt good.
打开雅加达那场比赛  第一轮
Play the Jakarta fight, round one.
打开了  爸爸
I have, papa.
拉到三分五十八秒
Go to three minutes 58 seconds.
你本来已经领先两分
You have a lead of two points,
然后你开始防守
and you started playing defensive.
你自己看
Play. Look.
然后就落后了  对吧
Threw away the lead, didn't you?
对手落后的情况下  你要一击致命
When the opponent is trailing, go for the jugular!
你怎么做到的
How did you do that?
该你防守的时候
Alternately, when you should be defending,
你却在进攻  这是在送分给对手
you are attacking and giving away points.
你一味追求分数  就得不到分
You will gain nothing by desperately chasing after points.
你应该要好好思考
You'll have to apply your mind.
你输掉的这些比赛本来都能赢
You've lost matches that were yours to win!
加油  吉塔
Go... Geeta!
全国选拔  帕蒂亚拉
"National Trials, Patiala"
每一轮都有两分钟
Each round consists of two minutes.
但是每个两分钟都有一百二十秒
However, there are 120 seconds in those two minutes.
你要等到对手犯错的那一秒
Wait for that one second when the opponent makes a mistake.
她很棒  对吧
She's good. Isn't she?
是的  先生
Yes, sir.
非常棒
Very good!
你已经准备好了  姐姐
Now you look ready, sis.
你给爸爸说了吗
Did you tell papa?
他说什么了
What did he say?
不要高兴得太早
"There's no need to get too happy!"
2010年英联邦运动会
2010年英联邦运动会盛大开幕
A grand opening ceremony to the 2010 Commonwealth Games!
主办国印度展示了她的古老文化
Host nation, India, displaying her ancient culture.
真是令人骄傲的一刻
A proud moment indeed!
向我们走来的是印度代表队
And here comes the Indian contingent!
热烈欢迎
A huge welcome for them.
请记住参加这次盛会的
Let us remind you that the finest athletes,
是来自72个国家最优秀的运动员
from 72 countries are participating.
明天比赛正式开始  我们明天再见
We'll be back tomorrow to start off the events.
再见  晚安
Until then... goodnight!
第一轮开始前吉塔看起来很紧张
Geeta was quite nervous before her first bout.
正如大家所料
And that was expected.
迄今为止在国际大赛中  她的表现平平
So far her performance in international events had been poor.
无论如何  大家依然对她满怀期待
However little... the nation still had hope on her.
而且这次也许是吉塔最后一次机会
And this was probably Geeta's last opportunity,
来证明她自己
to prove herself.
女子摔跤第一场
The first match in women's wrestling,
五十五公斤级  比赛双方分别是
55-kilo category, is between,
印度选手吉塔·库马莉
India's Geeta Kumari
和威尔士选手梅丽莎·安德森
and Melissa Anderson from Wales.
加油  吉塔
Go, Geeta!
吉塔看起来非常紧张
Geeta seems quite nervous.
现在我们来看看她是否能打破
Now, let's see if she can break her jinx,
第一轮被淘汰的魔咒
of losing in the first couple of rounds.
提醒一下各位观众
We would like to remind our spectators,
本次比赛共三轮  每轮两分钟
that there will be three rounds of two minutes each.
赢得两轮的选手最终赢得比赛
Whoever wins two rounds, wins the match.
现在比赛开始了
With that the match begins.
两名选手都非常警觉
Both the wrestlers are quite alert.
梅丽莎获得一分
1 point to Melissa.
梅丽莎一分  吉塔零分
Melissa - 1, Geeta - 0.
梅丽莎看起来更强壮
Melissa seems stronger.
梅丽莎获得三分
3 more points to Melissa!
你在干什么  吉塔
What are you doing, Geeta?
梅丽莎四分  吉塔零分
Melissa - 4, Geeta - 0.
如果吉塔再丢两分
If Geeta gives away 2 more points,
梅丽莎将以技术优势赢得本轮比赛
Melissa will win this round on technical superiority.
梅丽莎又获得两分
And Melissa gets 2 points!
正如我们所担心的一样
Exactly as we feared.
梅丽莎以6比0的技术优势赢得了本轮比赛
Melissa has won the first round on technical superiority, 6-0.
你在干什么  吉塔
What are you doing, Geeta?
不要输的这么难看
Don't lose so badly!
来看看在第一轮大比分落后的情况下
We now need to see that after losing the first round badly,
吉塔是否能在第二轮扭转战局
is Geeta capable of making a comeback in round two.
梅丽莎获得两分
2 points to Melissa.
梅丽莎再次获得一分
1 more point to Melissa.
看来这场比赛吉塔大势已去
The match seems to be slipping out of Geeta's hands.
你不会输的  吉塔
You are not to lose, Geeta!
加油  吉塔
Come on, Geeta.
吉塔在落后三分的情况下
Geeta, lagging by 3 points.
必须快速得分
She'll have to score real quick.
吉塔获得两分
2 points to Geeta!
梅丽莎三分  吉塔两分
Melissa - 3. Geeta - 2.
吉塔在尝试努力反击
Geeta tries to score some more,
但是裁判吹响了口哨
but the referee blows the whistle.
本轮比赛已经接近尾声
The round is nearing completion.
吉塔依然以一分之差落后
Geeta is still behind by a point.
吉塔这下麻烦了
Geeta in trouble!
吉塔得到三分
Geeta gets 3 points!
吉塔现在五分  梅丽莎三分
Geeta - 5, Melissa - 3.
还有四秒本轮比赛就结束了
Just four seconds to go.
太棒了  吉塔
Yes, Geeta!
吉塔终于找回了状态
Geeta's back in the match!
一比一平
It's one round each.
吉塔的表现说明她不会轻易接受失败
Geeta has shown that she is not going to accept defeat so easily.
现在是最后一轮比赛
It's the last round.
注意防守
Play defensive.
明白吗
Got it?
要进攻
Play attacking!
最后一轮比赛开始了
And the last round begins.
吉塔开始进攻
Geeta on the attack.
吉塔赢得一分
1 point for Geeta.
吉塔一分  梅丽莎零分
Geeta - 1, Melissa - 0.
吉塔又赢得两分
2 more points in Geeta's kitty.
吉塔现在三分  梅丽莎零分
Geeta-3, Melissa - 0.
她能否保持自己的优势呢
Will she manage to keep her lead?
非常好  现在开始防守
Very good. Defend now.
梅丽莎又获得三分
3 points for Melissa!
我给你说了要防守
I told you to defend.
没关系  继续进攻
No problem. Keep attacking!
比分现在是三比三平
The score is equal at 3-3.
加油  吉塔
Go for it, Geeta!
这场比赛结果仍然难料
This match can tilt either way.
吉塔胜利在望  但已丧失先机
Geeta was poised to win but lost her lead.
吉塔现在危险了
Geeta's in danger.
这招真漂亮
Wow! What a move!
吉塔获得三分
3 points to Geeta!
压倒她  吉塔
Keep her down, Geeta.
吉塔赢得了本次比赛
Geeta has won this match!
印度选手吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
India's Geeta Kumari Phogat,
证明了对她的批判都是错误的
has proven her critics wrong.
吉塔的父亲马哈维亚·辛格·珀尕
A proud moment for Geeta's father,
此刻一定很骄傲
Mahavir Singh Phogat!
迄今为止印度斩获了
So far India has won,
五金十三银七铜
five gold, 13 silver and seven bronze medals.
女子摔跤比赛中
In women's wrestling,
印度选手吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
India's Geeta Kumari Phogat,
挺进了五十五公斤级的半决赛
has entered the semi-finals of the 55-kilo category.
吉塔即将面对的是
Geeta will now face
尼日利亚选手内奥米·爱德华
Nigeria's Naomi Edwards,
后者曾两次获得世界冠军
two time world champion.
你有什么看法
What do you think?
内奥米是一个很强的摔跤选手
Naomi is a very strong wrestler.
及具侵略性和攻击性
Extremely aggressive and attacking.
她从不给她的对手任何机会
She doesn't give any opportunity to her opponent.
这场比赛对于吉塔来说会很困难
It's not going to be easy for Geeta this time.
今天你已经按你的意愿比了
Today, you played as per your will.
之后要按我说的来
Now, do as I say.
否则你根本赢不了
Or it's impossible to win.
这场比赛会很难
It's a difficult one,
但是也有赢面
but not impossible.
你必须以进攻为主
You'll have to play offensive!
你必须以防守为主
You have to play defensive.
一定要争取比分
Just go for the points!
不要只想着争取比分
Don't go for the points.
你会有很多机会
You'll get a lot of opportunities.
别给她任何机会  因为她不会给你机会
Don't give her any opportunities because she won't give you any.
每次的防守必须强硬
Force a lock-jam each time.
如果她得不到分  她就会很受挫
If she doesn't get to score, she'll get frustrated,
这时你的机会就来了
and will give you an opportunity.
我们必须抓住机会
That's the moment we should grab!
五十五公斤级第一场半决赛即将开始
The first semi-final match in the 55-kilo category.
印度选手吉塔·库马莉
India's Geeta Kumari
对战尼日利亚选手内奥米·爱德华
versus Nigeria's Naomi Edwards.
内奥米一开始就发起进攻
Naomi attacking from the start.
吉塔却反常地表现出了防守的架势
And against her nature, Geeta playing defensive.
内奥米发起了进攻
Naomi attacks!
吉塔麻烦了
Geeta in trouble.
吉塔的防守十分稳健
Geeta putting up a strong defense.
吉塔击退了对手的进攻
Geeta holding her back.
内奥米表现出强势的进攻
Naomi made a strong attempt.
但是吉塔稳住了
But Geeta held her own.
进攻啊
Go on the attack!
不要着急
Go easy.
内奥米表现得有些暴躁
Naomi gets rough.
她似乎受到了挫折
She seems frustrated.
内奥米扭了吉塔的手腕
Naomi twisting Geeta's wrist.
内奥米得到一个警告
Naomi is being given a warning.
坚持住  吉塔
Hang in there, Geeta!
内奥米得到了三分
That's 3 points for Naomi!
吉塔对她的阻挡十分不错
Geeta had been holding her off well.
她很努力防守
A really good effort,
但是内奥米打破了她的防守
but Naomi's broken through her defense.
吉塔必须要快速行动
Geeta has to act fast.
吉塔打倒了内奥米
Geeta takes Naomi down.
吉塔获得一分
1 point to Geeta!
她还在努力尝试
She's still trying.
可惜时间到了
And time's up!
吉塔做得很好  但是她输掉了第一轮
Geeta played well, but she's lost this first round.
你在干什么  吉塔
What are you doing, Geeta?
你为什么不进攻
Why don't you attack?
第二轮开始了
The second round begins.
内奥米发起了进攻
Naomi attacks.
内奥米试图绊倒吉塔
Naomi tries to flip Geeta.
但是吉塔防守很好
But Geeta defends well.
内奥米使出全力
Naomi puts all her strength,
但是吉塔没有给她任何机会
but Geeta isn't giving her a chance.
这是一场非常精彩的比赛
This is an exciting match.
内奥米在努力尝试
Naomi trying hard,
但是吉塔没有给她空间
but Geeta not giving her space.
内奥米再次发起进攻
Naomi attacks again.
吉塔防守
Geeta defends.
吉塔防得漂亮
A nice defense by Geeta.
裁判中断了她们
The referee breaks the fight.
第二轮仍然停留在零比零
Second round is still O-O.
内奥米一定在思考如何打破吉塔的防守
Naomi must be wondering how to break Geeta's defense.
如果她得不到分  她就会很受挫
"If she doesn't get to score, she'll get frustrated,
这时你的机会就来了
and will give you an opportunity."
内奥米发起了进攻
Naomi attacks.
我们必须抓住机会
"That's the moment we should grab!"
三分
3 Points!
吉塔以三比零赢得了这一轮
And Geeta wins this round, 3-0.
内奥米  看着我
Naomi, look at me.
那个姑娘很聪明
That girl, she's smart.
但是你更聪明
But you are double smart.
好吗
Okay?
不要让她那么容易翻转你
Don't allow her to turn you easily.
你是怎么打的
How are you fighting?
教练  我是按自己学到的技能比赛
Sir, I am fighting as I have learnt.
第三局  也就是最终局开始了
The third and final round has started.
很有意思
It's interesting to see,
内奥米也开始小心翼翼
that Naomi is now playing cautiously.
内奥米非常努力
Naomi trying real hard.
但是吉塔抱住了她的背
But Geeta holding her back.
又把她锁住了
It's a lock position again.
内奥米再次进攻
Naomi attacks again.
吉塔抱住她的背
Geeta holds her back.
内奥米能得分吗
Will Naomi score?
坚持住  吉塔
Hold on, Geeta!
比分依旧是零比零
The score stands at O-O.
内奥米攻势更甚
Naomi tries harder.
吉塔漏出破绽但仍死抱住她的背
Geeta is exposed here but holds her back.
吉塔在咬紧牙关坚持
Geeta hanging on by the skin of her teeth.
还剩12秒
Only 12 seconds left.
比分依旧是零比零
The score still 0-0.
吉塔进攻了
Geeta attacks!
目前本局比分依旧是零比零
With that this round is tied at 0-0.
她本来能得分的
She could have scored.
现在要掷硬币了
Now there'll be a toss.
要掷硬币
Now there will be a toss.
也就是缠抱
This is known as a 'clinch'.
掷硬币赢的一方选择抱对方哪一条腿
The wrestler who wins the toss gets to choose a grip,
有30秒时间争取得分
and gets 30 seconds to score.
如果红色向上  内奥米进攻
If the red side falls up, Naomi gets to attack,
蓝色向上  吉塔进攻
if it's blue, Geeta gets to attack.
掷硬币赢的人有99%的可能
In 99 percent of the cases the one who wins the toss,
赢得比赛
wins the match.
天啊
Oh!
或许命运也没有青睐吉塔
Maybe even destiny doesn't want Geeta to win.
抵抗内奥米进攻30秒简直是不可能的事
It's next to impossible to defend against Naomi for 30 seconds.
-你选哪条腿  -右腿
- Which leg do you choose? - Right.
内奥米选择了吉塔的右腿
Naomi has chosen Geeta's right leg.
吉塔摆出了防守姿态
Geeta takes a defensive position.
内奥米抓住了机会
Naomi takes her grip of choice.
现在  吉塔有两个选择
Now, Geeta has two options.
坚持30秒不让内奥米得分
Not allow Naomi to score for 30 seconds,
或者反守为攻  赢得比赛
or score herself, and win the match.
现在的情况下两个选择几乎都不可能
In this position against Naomi, both are almost impossible.
她举起了吉塔
She lifts Geeta!
吉塔得分
And Geeta scores a point!
吉塔的胜利出乎所有人意料
No one expected Geeta to win this match.
在这场激烈的缠抱对决中  她竟然
She has beaten the number one contender for gold,
战胜了排名第一的金牌竞争者
in this very exciting clinch,
并最终进入决赛
and entered the finals!
让我们期待吉塔·珀尕
And let's hope that Geeta Phogat,
在决赛中也保持良好状态
maintains her wonderful form in the finals too.
走吗  叔叔
Shall we go, uncle?
看看下一场比赛
Let's see the next match.
看看吉塔下一场要面对的是澳大利亚人
Let's find out whether Geeta's finals is against the Australian,
还是苏格兰人
or the Scottish wrestler.
我很为吉塔骄傲
I'm very proud of Geeta.
她在比赛中一直遵循我的策略
She followed my strategy to the end.
结果就摆在你们面前
The result is in front of you.
她来了
Here she comes.
她状态很棒
She looks good.
作为一个摔跤手
I mean... as a wrestler.
叔叔  她不就是DVD上那个
Uncle, isn't she the same one from the DVD?
安吉丽娜·沃森
Angelina Watson.
她两次击败过吉塔
She's defeated Geeta twice.
她直到现在状态都很棒
She's played well till now.
她也会在决赛中出色发挥
And she'll play well in the finals too.
我一直很信任吉塔
I've always had faith in Geeta.
她迟早能赢得国际奖牌
Sooner or later she had to win an international medal.
银牌肯定没问题
A silver is guaranteed now!
决赛不会那么简单
The final won't be so easy.
吉塔
Geeta-ji,
你的比赛发生了惊天逆转
your game has changed dramatically.
到底是怎么做到的
How did this happen?
所有的这一切
The entire credit for this,
都归功于我父亲
goes to my father.
他一直都很信任我
He never stopped believing in me.
马哈维亚
Mahavir-ji!
您好  沙米姆先生
Hello, Mr. Shamim.
恭喜你  马哈维亚
Congratulations, Mahavir-ji!
吉塔表现非常出色
Geeta fought very well.
整个巴拉里都为你骄傲
All of Balali is proud.
这些女孩子们都坚持
And these girls insisted,
要在体育馆里看吉塔的比赛
on watching Geeta's match in the stadium,
不然她们不吃饭
or they won't eat.
你觉得比赛怎么样
How did you like the match?
超赞的
Loved it!
请把这个给她
Give this to her.
这是什么
What is this?
我为她求的
I prayed for her.
明天就是决赛了
Tomorrow is the final.
祝你成功
Bless you!
怎么能允许这种事情发生  先生
How can we allow this, sir?
马哈维亚·辛格在观众席
Mahavir Singh is shouting
大呼小叫地给吉塔出主意
instructions to Geeta from the audience.
吉塔都迷惑了
The poor thing is getting
不知道该听他的还是我的
confused whether to listen to him or me.
从比赛来看  她似乎并不迷惑
From her game, it sure doesn't seem like she's confused.
再说  怎么能要求观众保持安静呢
Besides, how can we ask the audience to remain silent?
你不是教练吗
Aren't you the coach'?
她肯定听你的
She should be listening to you.
是的  先生  她的确听我的
No, sir... she is listening to me.
-所以她才能赢  -那还有什么问题
- That's why she's winning. - Then what's the problem?
你想得块铜牌  对吧
You wanted a bronze, right?
而她很有可能明天夺金
It's quite possible that tomorrow she may win gold.
不是吗
No?
她能走这么远我很惊讶  替她高兴
I'm surprised she's made it so far but I am happy for her.
明天决赛会很有意思
It should be an interesting final tomorrow.
在印度观众面前与印度人比试
Playing an Indian in front of an Indian crowd.
当然要打败她
Beating her, of course!
安吉丽娜  有压力吗
Angelina, any pressure before the finals?
有  我想她的压力会非常大
Yeah, I'm sure she must be under tremendous pressure.
我赢过她两次
I've beaten her twice.
第一轮  没错
First round? Yeah.
对  第一轮
Yeah, first round.
谢谢各位
So, thank you and,
合十礼
Namaste!
爸爸  明天应该采取什么策略
What's the strategy for tomorrow, papa?
孩子  明天你只有一个策略
There is only one strategy for tomorrow, child.
你需要让别人记住你
You have to fight in a way that people remember you.
如果只获得银牌
If you win silver,
你迟早会被人们忘记
sooner or later you'll be forgotten.
如果获得金牌  你将成为榜样
If you win gold, you will become an example.
榜样是树立起来的  不会被忘记
And examples are given, child... not forgotten.
看到那些女孩了吗
See those girls?
如果明天你赢了  你不是一个人赢
If you win tomorrow, you will not win alone.
很多像她们一样的女孩会分享你的胜利
Millions of girls like them will win along with you.
这场胜利  将会是
It'll be a victory for
所有被认为不如男孩的女孩的胜利
every girl who is considered inferior to boys;
她们被禁锢于家庭琐事
Who is forced into household chores,
结婚只为生儿育女
who is married off to just raise children.
明天的比赛是最重要的
Tomorrow's match is the most important one.
因为明天你要战胜的不仅仅是澳大利亚人
Because tomorrow you won't be fighting just that Australian
更是那些看轻女孩子的人
but all those people who think less of girls.
2010年英联邦运动会  女子摔跤
The finals of the women's wrestling, Commonwealth Games 2010,
五十五公斤级决赛即将开始
55-kilo category, is about to begin.
印度的吉塔·库马莉
India's Geeta Kumari
对阵澳大利亚的安吉丽娜·沃森
versus Australia's Angelina Watson.
请各位观众注意
We'd like to remind you all,
在英联邦运动会上  印度女子摔跤选手
that never before has an Indian female wrestler,
从未获得过金牌
ever won gold in the Commonwealth Games.
在人群中  我们看到了
In this crowd, we see,
希望  热情和印度国旗
a lot of hope, enthusiasm and the Indian flag.
先生您好
Hello, sir!
您是马哈维亚·辛格先生吗
Aren't you Mahavir Singh-ji?
-吉塔的父亲  -没错
- Geeta's father? - Yes.
请借一步说话
A moment please.
摔跤协会的主席想见见您
The chairman of the Wrestling Federation wants to meet you.
是很重要的事
Some important matter.
晚些再见  马上到我女儿比赛了
I'll meet him later. It's my daughter's match.
他可是大人物  可能会生气
He's a big man. He might get offended.
就几分钟时间
Just two minutes.
你去吧  我马上来
You carry on. I'll be there.
"所有的这一切都归功于我父亲"
"The entire credit for this goes to my father."
快去论功领赏吧
Go... take the credit.
还要多远
How much further is it'?
马上就到了  先生
We are almost there, sir.
你要带我去哪里
Where have you got me?
喂  老兄
Hey, brother!
你干什么  老兄
What are you doing, brother?
吉塔入场时掌声如潮
A thunderous applause for Geeta as she walks in.
有人吗
Is anyone there?
有人在吗
Hello!
有没有人
Anyone there?
这可是决赛
This is the final.
仔细打
Play carefully.
安吉丽娜·沃森入场
Angelina Watson enters the stadium.
决赛开始
And the final match begins.
勇夺金牌  吉塔
Go for gold, Geeta!
安吉丽娜一开始就攻势汹汹
Angelina, aggressive from the start.
她进攻了
She attacks.
吉塔防守
Geeta defends.
吉塔得三分
And 3 points for Geeta!
一开始吉塔就大比分领先
Geeta takes a big lead right from the start.
吉塔三分  安吉丽娜零分
Geeta - 3; Angelina - 0.
很好
Good... good!
吉塔再夺一分
Another point for Geeta.
吉塔四分  安吉丽娜零分
Geeta - 4; Angelina - 0.
吉塔表现出色
Geeta playing very well.
安吉丽娜必须加快速度
Angelina will need to act fast.
安吉丽娜一分
1 point to Angelina.
安吉丽娜在寻找抱摔机会
Angelina looks for a takedown.
吉塔拼命防守
Geeta defends we...
裁判员吹哨了
Referee whistles.
吉塔领先  四比一
Geeta leads, 4-1.
吉塔一分  吉塔五分  安吉丽娜一分
1 point to Geeta. Geeta-5; Angelina -1.
吉塔·库马莉轻松获得第一场比赛胜利
And with this, Geeta Kumari wins the first round quite easily.
或许安吉丽娜已经意识到了
Perhaps Angelina is realizing,
眼前的吉塔判若两人
that this is not the same Geeta,
已不再是过去可以轻易打败的对手
whom she had defeated easily in the past.
第二局开始
And the second round starts.
吉塔能否赢得本局创造历史呢
Will Geeta win this round and create history?
绝妙抱摔  吉塔一分
An excellent takedown! 1 point to Geeta.
吉塔一分  安吉丽娜零分
Geeta - 1; Angelina - 0.
加油  吉塔
Go... Geeta, go!
吉塔再得两分
2 more points for Geeta!
吉塔三分  安吉丽娜零分
Geeta - 3; Angelina - 0.
吉塔压制住了安吉丽娜
Geeta bearing down on Angelina.
吉塔进攻
Geeta attacks!
吉塔一分
1 point for Geeta.
再得两分
Two more points,
吉塔就能以技术优势赢得本局
and she'll win this round by technical superiority,
并且赢得冠军
and the championship!
吉塔全力压制
Geeta bearing down with all her might.
她会赢吗
Will Geeta win?
裁判员的哨声拯救了安吉丽娜
The referee's whistle saves Angelina!
没问题的  吉塔
No problem... Geeta!
安吉丽娜怒火中烧
Angelina seems furious.
安吉丽娜一分
1 point for Angelina.
安吉丽娜一分  吉塔四分
Angelina - 1; Geeta - 4.
吉塔身处险境
Geeta is still in danger.
安吉丽娜再得两分
2 more points for Angelina.
吉塔四分  安吉丽娜三分
Geeta - 4; Angelina - 3.
没问题的  加油
No problem... come on!
吉塔仍旧领先一分
Gee-ta still leads by 1 point.
她需要再坚持一会儿
She needs to hold on to it a little longer.
吉塔能保持领先优势吗
Will Geeta retain this lead?
时间流逝
Time is running out.
吉塔防守
Geeta defends we...
安吉丽娜全力出击
Angelina going all out.
安吉丽娜三分
3 points to Angelina!
安吉丽娜六分  吉塔四分
Angelina - 6; Geeta - 4.
这一局即将结束
And this round comes to an end.
安吉丽娜展现了冠军的实力
And Angelina has shown what a true champion is made of!
你在干什么  你可以赢的
What are you doing? You could've won the match!
安吉丽娜重燃斗志
Angelina, with renewed enthusiasm.
这一局对吉塔很是艰难
It's not going to be easy for Geeta.
安吉丽娜开局进攻
Angelina aggressive from the start.
安吉丽娜得三分
3 points for Angelina!
决赛中她领先三分
A 3-point lead in the final round!
安吉丽娜三分  吉塔零分
Angelina - 3; Geeta - O.
安吉丽娜再得一分
1 point more to Angelina.
安吉丽娜四分  吉塔零分
Angelina - 4; Geeta - O.
比赛的天秤向安吉丽娜倾斜
And this match leaning in favour of Angelina.
吉塔想要挽回颓势  就必须快速得分
If Geeta has to get back, she needs to score fast.
吉塔灵活周旋
A clever move by Geeta.
吉塔一分
1 point to Geeta!
安吉丽娜四分  吉塔一分
Angelina - 4; Geeta - 1.
时间流逝
Time... running out.
吉塔必须坚持下去
Geeta needs to keep at it.
但她必须小心  如果安吉丽娜再次得分
But carefully, because if Angelina scores again,
想挽回危局就不可能了
it'll be impossible to make a come back.
吉塔进攻
Geeta attacks,
但安吉丽娜再得一分
but Angelina scores a point!
安吉丽娜五分  吉塔一分
Angelina - 5; Geeta - 1.
吉塔想要卷土重来几乎已不可能
It's almost impossible now for Geeta to make a comeback!
"记住"
"Remember!"
"爸爸不可能在每次危难时刻都来救你"
"Your papa won't be there to save you every time."
"我只能告诉你怎么战斗"
"I can only teach you to fight."
"但你必须自己去战斗"
"But you have to fight yourself."
"努力拼搏  拯救自己"
"Make the effort... save yourself."
还剩22秒
Only 22 seconds left.
吉塔还落后四分
And Geeta is trailing by 4 points.
在这个公斤级  这么短的时间内
At this level, it's almost
吉塔想反超比分几乎不可能
impossible to cover this lead in such short time.
"得五分很难"
"To score five points is difficult,
"但并非不可能"
but it can be done."
吉塔在寻找机会
Geeta trying.
但安吉丽娜在拖延时间
But Angelina stalling for time.
还剩下几秒
Just a few seconds left.
印度或许只好接受银牌的命运
And India might have to settle for a silver.
"你要迷惑对手"
"You have to play with the opponent's mind."
"做假动作
"Fake a move,
然后冲向另一边"
but make another."
吉塔做了漂亮的假动作
And a fantastic move by Geeta.
时间能站在她这边吗
Will time be on her side?
吉塔获得金牌
It's a gold for Geeta!
她完成了不可能完成之事
Geeta has achieved the impossible!
她是印度历史上第一个
She is the first ever female Indian wrestler,
获得英联邦运动会金牌的女摔跤手
to win gold at the Commonwealth Games!
谁会料到一个来自印度小乡村的女孩
Who would have thought that a girl from a small village in India,
能够让全世界都记住她
is capable of leaving her mark on the whole world!
干得好  吉塔
Well done, Geeta!
真是印度历史上的辉煌时刻
A proud moment for India indeed!
冠军
Champion!
爸爸
Where's Papa?
我不知道
I don't know.
不过我们是一起来的
We came together though.
现在  有请金牌得主
And now the gold medal,
印度选手吉塔·库马莉·珀尕
for India's Geeta Kumari Phogat.
现在  作为运动会传统
And now, as per tradition,
将播放获胜者国家的国歌
the national anthem of the winning country will play.
印度获胜
Victory to India!
你在这里干什么
Hey! What are you doing here?
吉塔  快过来  媒体在等你
Geeta, come... the media is waiting.
快过来
Come.
来吧  大家都在等你
Come. Everyone is waiting.
过来
Come... come.
终于  我叔叔开了金口
And finally uncle uttered those golden words,
说出了那句我们渴盼十年的话
that we had been pining to hear for the past 10 years.
我为你骄傲
I'm proud of you!